[
    {
        "question": "Zomato has launched  \u2018Zomato Quick\u2019, an in-App 10-Minute Food Delivery Service in Multiple Cities.Who among the following is the founder and CEO of Zomato?",
        "options": [
            "Deepinder Goyal ",
            "Kunal Shah ",
            "Ashutosh Kumar ",
            "Rohit Kapoor "
        ],
        "answer": "Deepinder Goyal ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Railway Ministry has launched the SwaRail app, a SuperApp designed to provide a one-stop solution for a range of public services. SwaRail app is developed by which organisation?",
        "options": [
            "Container Corporation of India Limited (CONCOR) ",
            "IRCON International Limited ",
            "Dedicated Freight Corridor Corporation of India (DFCCIL) ",
            "Centre for Railway Information Systems (CRIS) "
        ],
        "answer": "Centre for Railway Information Systems (CRIS) ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following has imposed a monetary penalty of Rs 9.27 crore on virtual digital asset service provider Bybit Fintech Limited for violations of its obligations under the PMLA?",
        "options": [
            "Reserve Bank of India (RBI) ",
            "Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)  ",
            "Competition Commission of India (CCI)  ",
            "Financial Intelligence Unit-India (FIU-IND) "
        ],
        "answer": "Financial Intelligence Unit-India (FIU-IND) ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country will be host Asian Games in 2025?",
        "options": [
            "France  ",
            "United States  ",
            "China  ",
            "Japan ",
            "is testing eSakshya (e-evidence) app. ",
            "will be available to all "
        ],
        "answer": "China  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which city is the host of first Raisina Middle East Conference?",
        "options": [
            "Abu Dhabi ",
            "Riyadh ",
            "Cairo ",
            "Beirut "
        ],
        "answer": "Abu Dhabi ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been named as the pilot for Axiom Mission 4 (Ax-4)?",
        "options": [
            "Mohana Singh ",
            "Narinder Chatrath ",
            "Aruna Kumar Datta ",
            "Shubhanshu Shukla "
        ],
        "answer": "Shubhanshu Shukla ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which three countries have withdrawn from the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) in January 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Nigeria, Ghana, Togo ",
            "Senegal, Guinea, Liberia ",
            "Mali, Burkina Faso, Niger ",
            "Benin, Cote d\u2019Ivoire, Sierra Leone "
        ],
        "answer": "Mali, Burkina Faso, Niger ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country has been certified malaria-free by the World Health Organization (WHO) in January 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Azerbaijan ",
            "Georgia ",
            "Armenia ",
            "Moldova  "
        ],
        "answer": "Georgia ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country is the host of Africa Energy Summit 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Tanzania ",
            "Botswana ",
            "Egypt ",
            "Sudan "
        ],
        "answer": "Tanzania ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the rate of interest applicable on the Government of India Floating Rate Bonds, 2035 (GOI FRB 2035) for the period January 25, 2025, to January 24, 2030?",
        "options": [
            "6.25% ",
            "6.50% ",
            "6.66% ",
            "7.10% "
        ],
        "answer": "6.66% ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which financial institutions has invested \u20b9830 crore in Aditya Birla Housing Finance Ltd. (ABHFL) through non-convertible debentures (NCDs)?",
        "options": [
            "World Bank (WB) ",
            "Asian Development Bank (ADB) ",
            "International Finance Corporation (IFC) ",
            "International Monetary fund (IMF) "
        ],
        "answer": "International Finance Corporation (IFC) ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company has partnered with X to introduce a real-time payment system?",
        "options": [
            "Mastercard ",
            "Visa ",
            "PayPal ",
            "American Express "
        ],
        "answer": "Visa ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which astronaut holds the record for most spacewalks by a woman in space?",
        "options": [
            "Peggy Whitson ",
            "Sunita Williams ",
            "Svetlana Savitskaya ",
            "Sally Ride "
        ],
        "answer": "Sunita Williams ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which bank won top honours in six categories at the 2024 IBA Banking Technology Awards?",
        "options": [
            "ICICI Bank ",
            "HDFC Bank ",
            "State Bank of India ",
            "Karnataka Bank "
        ],
        "answer": "Karnataka Bank ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new CEO of Sony?",
        "options": [
            "Hiroki Totoki ",
            "Kenichiro Yoshida ",
            "Hideaki Nishino ",
            "Hermen Hulst "
        ],
        "answer": "Hiroki Totoki ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "In February 2025, Four new wetlands from India have been added to the list of Ramsar sites. Which of the given options is not true with respect to the location of these wetlands?",
        "options": [
            "Sakkarakottai Bird Sanctuary - Tamil Nadu  ",
            "Therthangal Bird Sanctuary - Tamil Nadu  ",
            "Khecheopalri Wetland - Manipur  ",
            "Udhwa Lake - Jharkhand "
        ],
        "answer": "Khecheopalri Wetland - Manipur  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the first wetland of Jharkhand to be included in the Ramsar Wetland site list?",
        "options": [
            "Topchanchi Lake ",
            "Kalindi Lake ",
            "Manjura Lake ",
            "Udhwa Lake "
        ],
        "answer": "Udhwa Lake ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is the first wetland of Sikkim to be included in the Ramsar wetlands list ?",
        "options": [
            "Tso Lhamo Lake ",
            "Khecheopalri Lake ",
            "Tsongmo Lake ",
            "Gurudongmar Lake "
        ],
        "answer": "Khecheopalri Lake ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state in India has the highest number of wetlands under the Ramsar sites?",
        "options": [
            "Uttar Pradesh  ",
            "Tamil Nadu  ",
            "Karnataka  ",
            "Madhya Pradesh "
        ],
        "answer": "Tamil Nadu  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recently four new wetlands from India have been added to the Ramsar sites list. What is the total Ramsar sites tally so far in India?",
        "options": [
            "85 ",
            "93 ",
            "81 ",
            "89 "
        ],
        "answer": "89 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "With reference to Very Short-Range Air Defence System, consider the following statements:  1. It is a Man Portable Air Defence system.  2. It is short-range, lightweight and portable surface-to-air missile.  3. It is designed and developed indigenously.  Follow us: Official Site, Telegram, Facebook, Instagram, Youtube 21   Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 and 2 only ",
            "2 and 3 only ",
            "1, 2 and 3 ",
            "None "
        ],
        "answer": "1, 2 and 3 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the National Bank for Financing Infrastructure and Development (NaBFID), recently seen in the news:  1. It is a specialized Development Finance Institution in India aimed at supporting the country's infrastructure sector.  2. It is regulated and supervised by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI).  3.The authorized share capital of the NaBFID is Rs one lakh crore.  4.The initial paid-up capital of NaBFID is Rs 20,000 crore.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            ", recently seen in the news: ",
            "1, 2 and 3 only ",
            "2, 3 and 4 only ",
            "3 and 4 only  ",
            "1, 2, 3 and 4 "
        ],
        "answer": "3 and 4 only  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the RBI's Digital Payments Index:  1. It is constructed to measure the extent of digitisation of payments across the country.  2. It has been constructed with March 2020 as the base year.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "1 only ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Etemad and Ghadr-380 missiles, recently seen in the news, are developed by which one of the following countries?",
        "options": [
            "France ",
            "Turkey ",
            "United Arab Emirates ",
            "Iran "
        ],
        "answer": "Iran ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding Small Modular Reactors (SMRs):  1.Finance Minister announced a \u20b920,000 crore \u2018Nuclear Energy Mission\u2019 to develop indigenous Small Modular Reactors (SMR).  2. They are small nuclear reactors with a maximum output of 300 Megawatt electric (MWe).  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding Pradhan Mantri Shram Yogi Maandhan Yojana (PM-SYM):  1. It is a Central Sector Scheme administered by the Ministry of Labour and Employment.  2. All unorganized workers above 18 years of age are eligible for social security under the PM-SYM. \u27a2 India has conducted the first successful flight test of nuclear ballistic missile Agni-5. Agni-5 missile developed under Make in India project by DRDO. \u27a2 Agni 5 missile is the longest range missile of the Agni series with a range of over 5000 km.  Follow us: Official Site, Telegram, Facebook, Instagram, Youtube 28   Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "1 only ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the SwaRail Application:  1. It integrates various railway services by eliminating the need for multiple applications.  2. It is developed by the Centre for Railway Information Systems (CRIS).  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "With reference to the Pradhan Mantri Dhan Dhanya Krishi Yojana, recently seen in the news, consider the following:  1. Enhance agricultural productivity  2. Improve irrigation facilities  3. Improve credit availability  4. To adopt crop diversification  5. To augment post-harvest storage  How many of the given above are key focus areas of Pradhan Mantri Dhan Dhanya Krishi Yojana?",
        "options": [
            "1, 2 and 3 ",
            "2, 3 and 4 ",
            "3, 4 and 5 ",
            "1,2,3,4 and 5 "
        ],
        "answer": "1,2,3,4 and 5 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary aim of the Bharatiya Bhasha Pustak Scheme, recently seen in the news?",
        "options": [
            "To offer subsidized printed books to students in rural areas. ",
            "To replace physical textbooks with digital ones. ",
            "To offer digital textbooks and study materials in various Indian languages. ",
            "None of the above. "
        ],
        "answer": "To offer digital textbooks and study materials in various Indian languages. ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Inland mangrove of Guneri, recently in news, is located in:",
        "options": [
            "Karnataka ",
            "West Bengal ",
            "Tamil Nadu ",
            "Gujarat "
        ],
        "answer": "Gujarat ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the National Manufacturing Mission:  1. It will lay emphasis on future ready workforce for in-demand jobs.  2. It aims to enhance domestic value addition and build a robust ecosystem for solar PV cells.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the National Geospatial Mission:  1. It is aimed at modernising land records and enhancing urban planning across India.  2. It will leverage the existing PM Gati Shakti framework to develop foundational geospatial infrastructure and data.   Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which team won the 6th Men\u2019s Hockey India League 2024-25?",
        "options": [
            "Shrachi Rarh Bengal Tigers ",
            "Hyderabad Toofans ",
            "Dabang Mumbai ",
            "Punjab Warriors  "
        ],
        "answer": "Shrachi Rarh Bengal Tigers ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Indian women's team defeated which team in the final to win their second consecutive ICC Women's U19 T20 World Cup title?",
        "options": [
            "Australia  ",
            "Bangladesh  ",
            "South Africa  ",
            "England "
        ],
        "answer": "South Africa  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the mascot of the 9th Winter Asian Games 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Binbin and Nini ",
            "Fu Niu and Lele ",
            "Bing Dwen and Shuey Rhon ",
            "Shuey Rhon and Binbin  "
        ],
        "answer": "Binbin and Nini ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country will host the 10th Winter Asian Games in 2029?",
        "options": [
            "UAE  ",
            "Saudi Arabia  ",
            "Qatar  ",
            "United States "
        ],
        "answer": "Saudi Arabia  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "The World Wetlands Day is observed every year on which day?",
        "options": [
            "February 04 ",
            "February 02 ",
            "February 03 ",
            "February 01 "
        ],
        "answer": "February 02 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    }
]